{"tossups": [{"question": "1. Description acceptable. The sudden execution of this action over the October 6, 1979 weekend was called the Saturday Night Special. During the \u201cstop-go\u201d policy era, this kind of action characterized the \u201cstop\u201d phase and its opposite the \u201cgo\u201d phase. During the Great Moderation, this specific action was undertaken when actual output exceeded potential output, thereby following the Taylor Rule. Though not related to foreign policy, this strategy has historically been supported by so-called \u201chawks\u201d in response to fears of (*) bubbles. Since December 2015, this action has been taken six times to move away from the zero lower bound, a strategy Jerome Powell is continuing. The 1981 to 1982 recession resulted from Paul Volcker performing this action, which caused a change of around 1000 basis points that was applauded by advocates of \u201cWhip Inflation Now!\u201d For 10 points, identify this action taken by the Federal Reserve to increase the cost of borrowing money.", "answer": "the Federal Reserve Board of Governors raising interest rates [accept obvious equivalents like rate hikes in place of \u201craising the interest rate\u201d; accept the Federal Open Market Committee or the FOMC in place of \u201cFed\u201d; prompt on partial answers; accept the federal funds rate or the discount rate in place of \u201cinterest rate\u201d; prompt on decreasing the money supply or decreasing M0 or decreasing M1 or decreasing M2 or contractionary monetary policy or tightening monetary policy and obvious equivalents; prompt on answers like combating inflation before \u201cinflation\u201d is mentioned; prompt on open market operations] &lt;AA, US History&gt;", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "2. Semiotics was applied to the deconstruction of this profession by J. B. Harley, who wrote several volumes on its history. In the 18th century, a standard in this profession named for Rigobert Bonne replaced one named for Johannes Werner. The Pizigano brothers worked in this profession. Charles Hapgood cited Piri Reis\u2019s work in this profession to promote conspiracy theories. The so-called \u201cMajorcan\u201d school of this profession, mostly made of Catalonian Jews, included (*) Abraham Cresques. Medieval members of this profession made heavy use of a so-called \u201cT-O\u201d pattern and created numerous portolans. A man of this profession honored Amerigo Vespucci by using the term \u201c America\u201d on his Universalis Cosmographia. For 10 points, name this profession of Martin Waldseemuller and Gerardus Mercator.", "answer": "cartography [or cartographer; accept any answer that indicates the making of maps; prompt on geography or geographer] &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "History Other", "category": "History"}, {"question": "3. In one essay, this author attacks the writings of Jules Michelet and calls his History of France riddled with \u201cperilous openings for assault.\u201d That essay begins with the line \u201cWhat is to be thought of her?\u201d referencing a girl from Lorraine who rose to the \u201cperilous station at the right hand of kings.\u201d Another essay by this author includes sections titled \u201cThe Vision of Sudden Death\u201d and \u201cDream-Fugue,\u201d and was published in Blackwood\u2019s Magazine, as was his earlier essay (*) \u201cSuspiria de Profundis.\u201d This author of an essay on \u201cJoan of Arc\u201d recounts meeting Ann, a 16-year-old prostitute, on the corner of Oxford Street in another work. In that work, this author described the time when he gave a package load of a certain substance to a traveling Malay and how he began using that title substance to help him deal with his chronic stomach pains. For 10 points, name this author of Confessions of an English Opium Eater.", "answer": "Thomas De Quincey &lt;SB, Essays/Crit&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "4. An inscription records that a king of this empire threw the biggest rager of all time, with 10,000 measures of beer and 10,000 containers of wine serving 47,074 invitees. The Black Obelisk from this empire is a contemporary source on Jehu\u2019s reign. Accounts of invasions by this empire written by king Taharqa record that its armies had their bowstrings eaten by field mice. This empire\u2019s first recorded king heavily propagandized his smashing of the (*) Kassites and conquered the vassal rulers of the rump of the Mitanni kingdom; that ruler was Adad-Nirari I. The \u201cTaylor,\u201d \u201cOriental Institute,\u201d and \u201cJerusalem\u201d Prisms contain the propagandistic \u201cAnnals\u201d of a king of this empire, which insist that Hezekiah was made a tributary subject and never dealt this empire a defeat. For 10 points, name this empire led by Sennacherib and Ashurbanipal.", "answer": "Assyrian Empire [or Ashur] &lt;WA, Historical Sources&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "5. The alternate ending for one novella by this man changes a self-inflicted gunshot to one aimed at the protagonist\u2019s mistress. After dancing with that mistress at a village festival in that novella, Eugene calls her the title word, accusing her of \u201cpossessing\u201d him against his will. In another of this author\u2019s novellas, a character elbows his wife in the face, strangles, and stabs her before entering his study to commit suicide, but instead ends up falling asleep for two hours. This author wrote of the peasant girl (*) Stepanida\u2019s allure in The Devil and created the violinist Troukhatchevsky who hides under a piano while trying to escape the insanely jealous Pozdnyshev. In another novella by this author, Gerasim tends to the title character, who suffers a terminal illness after falling while trying to hang curtains. For 10 points name this author of the Kreutzer Sonata and the Death of Ivan Ilyich.", "answer": "Leo Tolstoy [or Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy] &lt;SB, Short Fiction&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "6. A different author\u2019s poem \u201cRacing Stars\u201d describes [emphasize] this author composing a poem in which the speaker\u2019s chest is ripped open by a snake, who deposits a \u201cblazing shard of coal\u201d before being called to \u201cburn Man\u2019s heart\u201d with God\u2019s word. This author of \u201cThe Prophet\u201d died \u201cwith lead in breast and vengeful fire\u201d due to \u201cgossip\u201d according to a poem that opens \u201cThe Bard is dead!\u201d That poem about this author is titled (*) \u201cThe Death of the Poet.\u201d A narrative poem by this author contrasts the \u201ceternal sleep\u201d of the nature-conquering Peter with a river that \u201churls itself\u201d on the city that Peter built. In that poem, a man witnesses the demise of his beloved Parasha in the flood of the Neva before being chased by the title statue. For 10 points, name this author of \u201cThe Bronze Horseman.\u201d", "answer": "Alexander Pushkin (\u201cRacing Stars\u201d is by Vladimir Nabokov.) &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "7. Juan Ram\u00f3n Jim\u00e9nez may have coined the term \u201cnaked poetry\u201d after translating Poem 7 from one collection by this author, which describes removing adornments from song. Many of this author\u2019s works were published in Prabasi magazine, where he himself published the works of Lalon. This author wrote that \u201cthe time has come when badges of honor make our shame glaring\u201d in a letter to Lord Chelmsford, in which he rejected a previous knighthood after a 1919 (*) massacre in his country. He wrote of a place \"where the mind is without fear and the head is held high\" and asked that \"into that heaven of freedom, Father, let my country awake.\" W.\u00a0B.\u00a0Yeats wrote that he would close man's manuscripts on the bus, \u201clest some stranger would see how much it moved\u201d him, in the introduction to a poetry collection by this author. For 10 points, name this \u201cBard of Bengal,\u201d the author of Gitanjali.", "answer": "Rabindranath Tagore [or Rav\u012bndran\u0101tha \u1e6ch\u0101kura] &lt;SB, Authors/Bios&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "8. Description acceptable. People who took part in this process are the subject of a landmark study by St. Clair Drake and Horace Cayton, whose work was funded by the Works Progress Administration. Isabel Wilkerson interviewed over 1,200 people to write a history of this historical process titled The Warmth of Other Suns. A 2015 exhibit united 60 different works of art depicting this process split between the Phillips Gallery and MoMA. This process is responsible for creating such areas as (*) Bronzeville and Hunters Point, the latter of which coalesced around a World War II shipyard in San Francisco. Participants in this broader process include \u201cKing\u201d Oliver\u2019s jazz band, which found work in Chicago. For 10 points, name this major demographic shift in the early 20th century depicted on a series of murals by Jacob Lawrence, which involved much of the South\u2019s population going north.", "answer": "The Great Migration [accept answers that indicate a migration of African-Americans out of the South in the early 20th century; prompt on migration or Migration Series] (Drake and Cayton\u2019s book is titled Black Metropolis.) &lt;WA, Historiography&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "9. In No Longer at Ease, a taxi driver goes out of his way to run over one of these animals since, unlike a duck, running over this animal will bring good luck for a new car. One of these animals keeps the newborn child of Bjartur warm after his wife dies during childbirth in Halldor Laxness\u2019 Independent People. The sudden explosive death of one of these animals upsets the security guard Tamaru and may have caused Tsubasa to leave the dowager's house in 1Q84. \u201cHe had been alive. He was now dead\u201d are some of the last lines in a (*) biography of one of these animals written by Virginia Woolf. In another novel, the autistic Christopher learns about his mother\u2019s affair with Mr. Shears while investigating the death of one of these animals that had been speared by a garden fork. For 10 points, name this animal whose \u201ccurious incident\u201d is explored in the \u201cnight-time\u201d in a book by Mark Haddon.", "answer": "dogs [anti-prompt on specific types of dogs] &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "10. A group of Somalis attempting to migrate to this country began a hunger strike after being held in Villawood. A series of riots by people attempting to enter this country began after Joshua Kaluvia and Louie Efi murdered the 23-year-old Reza Berati. The method for handling immigrants to this nation was drastically changed after an incident in which the Norwegian ship MV Tampa was turned away. Ashmore Island and Cartier Island were excised from this country\u2019s namesake (*) \u201cMigration Zone.\u201d The PNG solution was one attempt to stem asylum seekers to this nation, which previously held them in detention centers on Nauru and Manus Island. For 10 points, name this Anglophone country which regularly receives asylum seekers or \u201cboat people\u201d from Indonesia and Southeast Asia.", "answer": "(Commonwealth of) Australia &lt;EM, British/Other History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "11. Contemporary writers noted that this man frequently appealed to people by baring his thigh and slapping it in public, as well as using the innovative tactic of gesturing and walking around while speaking. This man filed a lawsuit over a satirical depiction of him in the play The Babylonians. This man is condemned to work at the city gates after his downfall in a play in which youth is restored to the old man Demos. In that play, the Paphlagonian oracle is stolen by (*) two slaves who depict this man\u2019s political contemporaries Nicias and Demosthenes. This man is replaced in office by the sausage-seller Agoracitus in a play that was intended to attack his motivations for taking a populist, pro-war position on the Peloponnesian War. For 10 points, name this Athenian politician brutally satirized by Aristophanes in The Knights.", "answer": "Cleon &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "category": "History"}, {"question": "12. Select persecution of Sufis in this empire benefited Khalid Shahrazuri, whose Naqshbandi followers were allowed to take over many lodges. A preacher in this empire organized disgruntled peasant mercenaries called sekban into a series of tax revolts. In the Shahkulu revolt against this empire, many Shi\u2019a joined forces with members of a syncretic Muslim tradition prominent in this empire\u2019s homeland. This (*) non-Persian empire persecuted the remaining qizilbash in lands that it gained following its decisive victory at the Battle of Chaldiran. Mass murder committed by this empire drove the Alevis underground. Religious minority groups in this empire were governed under the millet system. For 10 points, name this empire whose devshirme system turned Christian minority children into Janissaries.", "answer": "Ottoman Empire [or Devlet-i \u2018Al\u012bye-i \u2018Osm\u0101n\u012bye] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "13. In this novel, a cat destroys one character\u2019s Polish pigskin briefcase and tears apart a report about the Bipartite Para-Models of Missile Flight. A character in this novel names his pet spider \u201cEasy Rider\u201d at the behest of his 6-year-old son Paul. A man in this novel, who is described as a \u201cgood atheist jew,\u201d fails to persuade Ed to continue their homosexual relationship and leaves his job at the Datatronics company. In this novel, a drummer for the punk band (*) Liquid Sheep posts a dating advertisement for her friend to the personals section of the Bay Guardian. Father O\u2019Hare leads a march against the Lungless Labs in this novel, which becomes a central point of conflict between the main character of this novel and his lover, Liz Dorati. This novel focuses on the virulent anti-peacenik, John Brown, and is composed of 590 Onegin stanzas. For 10 points, name this verse novel by Vikram Seth.", "answer": "The Golden Gate &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Note to players: ethnicity and polity required. Aspiring mathematical students from this group were denied entry to their country\u2019s mathematical institutes through deceptively simple \u201ccoffin problems.\u201d In his memoir Love and Math, a Berkeley mathematician described his experience of systemic discrimination as a member of this group. This specific group was the impetus for passing the Jackson\u2013Vanik amendment. The movement Nativ specifically sought to contact these people. The most famous subgroup of the (*) refuseniks was this ethnic group, whose namesake movement in the United States advocated that they pursue aliyah. The \u201cSecret Letter\u201d alleged that doctors of this group planned to poison Joseph Stalin. For 10 points, name this ethnic group that, under the previous government, was confined to the Pale of Settlement by Catherine the Great.", "answer": "Soviet Jews [or the Soviet Jewry Movement; accept clear equivalents like Jews from the Soviet Union; accept Union of Soviet Socialist Republics or USSR or Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik or CCCP in place of the Soviet Union; accept Ashkenazi Jews or Ashkenazim in place of \u201cJews\u201d; accept refuseniks before it is read; prompt on Russian Jews; prompt on Jews in the Eastern Bloc or Jews in the Warsaw Pact] &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "15. Wilfred Thesiger described the practice in this region of building large stone cairns called waidellas. Archaeological evidence suggests that the port of Zeila was used to export the products of salt mines in this region\u2019s Danakil desert. Though not in Tanzania, this region is home to the oldest known deposits of Olduwan style tools. In this region, Zeremsaray Alemseged discovered the oldest known fossil of a hominid child and gave it the name Selam. Many fossils have been discovered in this region by the Middle Awash project. This region lends its name to a (*) species of hominid discovered by Donald Johanson and named after a Beatles song; that fossil, Lucy, is from this region\u2019s namesake Australopithecus species. For 10 points, name this roughly triangular area of low land in northern Ethiopia and Eritrea.", "answer": "Afar Depression [or Afar Triangle; accept Australopithecus afarensis; prompt on Ethiopia or East Africa] &lt;WA, Archaeology&gt;", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "16. Two followers of a man actually named Lucifer of Cagliari listed numerous shortcomings of a holder of this title in the Libellus Precum. A holder of this title named Hormisdas helped end a dispute that broke out after the Henotikon failed to broker agreement. A popular legend claims that holders of this title had to sit on a chair with a hole in it and have their genitals felt to ensure they were male. A man with this title (*) negotiated with Genseric to preserve a city\u2019s ancient buildings from a sack, and led an embassy which convinced the loser at Catalaunian fields to turn home. Lorenzo Valla debunked a forgery that claimed Constantine I transferred authority of the Western empire to a holder of this title. For 10 points, name this title held by the successor to Saint Peter, the first Bishop of Rome.", "answer": "popes [or pappas or papa; accept antipope or antipapas] &lt;WA, Ancient History&gt;", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "17. While a woman and a fish seller squabble in a play by this author, the title character is able to escape through an open window and successfully evade one of the sinister \u201cdaughters of Eve.\u201d After being told that people like to be remembered by what they leave behind, a character in a play by this author asks \u201cwho does not seek to be remembered? Memory is the master of death.\u201d This author created a character who tells the tale of a bird that flies around the world to inform people of their impending (*) death, but each time receives the response \u201cNot I.\u201d Olunde mistakenly believes that a change in the sound of the drums means that his father has died in a play by this author. Simon Pilkings looks to put a stop to the ritual suicide of Elesin Oba in that play by this author. For 10 points, name this Nigerian playwright of Death and the King\u2019s Horseman.", "answer": "Wole Soyinka &lt;SB, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "18. Terrorists of this ethnicity were responsible for the 1968 bombing of a Bank of Tokyo Trust office at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. Prisoners of this ethnicity started a 1987 riot in Atlanta when told they could be repatriated. The terrorist groups Omega 7 and Alpha 66 were primarily composed of people of this ethnicity. Several children of this ethnicity were brought to the United States in Operation Peter Pan, many of whom migrated to Union City, New Jersey. A mass movement of these people into the US was triggered by Hector (*) Sanyustiz driving a bus through the walls of an embassy. Janet Reno had a child of this ethnicity returned to his home country in a high-profile custody case in 2000. The Mariel Boatlift affected these people, who include Elian Gonzalez. For 10 points, name this ethnic group whose members include Rafael Cruz, many of whom came to Florida after Castro came to power.", "answer": "Cuban-Americans [prompt on Latin-Americans or Hispanics or Latinos or Latinx or similar answers] &lt;EM, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "19. In a novel from this country, a lengthy lawsuit about a man\u2019s death from poisoning is marred by the revelation that a boy had premarital sex with the daughter of a nyai. That novel\u2019s author recounted fourteen years of political imprisonment in The Mute\u2019s Soliloquy. D. H. Lawrence\u2019s preface to a novel set in this modern day country identifies a \u201cpassionate, honourable hate\u201d like that of Swift or Gogol in an idyllic scene about Sa\u00efdjah [sah-EED-yah] and Adinda. This country is the setting of a coming-of-age novel about the boy Minke titled (*) This Earth of Mankind and the other novels in the Buru Quartet. A colonial system of agriculture used in this country, the \u201cCultivation System,\u201d is exploited by the merchant Drystubble in a satire of the coffee industry here by Edward Dekker. For 10 points, the novel Max Havelaar by Multatuli depicts Dutch colonialism in what Asian country?", "answer": "(Republic of) Indonesia (the Buru Quartet is by Pramoedya Ananta Toer) &lt;WA, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "20. This character reflects religious women key to Nile fertility rites, according to Elizabeth Drew\u2019s book on \u201cthe design of the poetry\u201d of her creator. Grover Smith\u2019s article on this character introduced a myth that she was based on a woman from Ecbatana in Aldous Huxley\u2019s Crome Yellow. She may refer to a da Vinci work by noting \u201cHere is Belladonna, the Lady of the Rocks\u201d and speaks of a \u201cone-eyed (*) merchant\u201d who is later represented as Smyrna native Mr. Eugenides. This character notes \u201cThose are pearls that were his eyes. Look!\u201d about a figure who is later incarnated as the Phoenician Phlebas, the Drowned Sailor. This character is known as the \u201cwisest woman in Europe\u201d and has a \u201cmean pack of cards.\u201d For 10 points, name this \u201cfamous clairvoyant\u201d from T.\u00a0S. Eliot\u2019s \u201cThe Waste Land.\u201d", "answer": "Madame Sosostris [prompt on Madame] &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "21. A letter by this politician to activist Arthur Young was published alongside a piece opposing an agricultural minimum wage titled Thoughts and Details on Scarcity. The cartoon Cincinnatus in Retirement lampoons this politician\u2019s support for Catholic Emancipation. This politician wrote that \u201cA state without the means of some change is without the means of its conservation\u201d in a work that notes \u201cthe age of chivalry is gone.\u201d This politician criticized colleagues\u2019 punitive fiscal measures in the (*) Speech on American Taxation, which was later followed by his Speech on Conciliation with America. This fierce opponent of Warren Hastings criticized Richard Price\u2019s abstract principles of the \u201crights of man\u201d in a piece of invective against Jacobin thuggery. For 10 points, name this author of Reflections on the Revolution in France.", "answer": "Edmund Burke &lt;WA, Phil/SS&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "22. This phenomenon is [emphasize] contrasted with one that is \u201cconsidered a promotion\u201d when experienced by Hans Castorp in a book that illustrates attitudes about this phenomenon with a line from W. H. Auden\u2019s \u201cMiss Gee\u201d about how this is a \u201cfunny thing.\u201d A book exploring this phenomenon\u2019s \u201cmythology\u201d argues it was considered appropriate for \u201clife\u2019s losers,\u201d but inappropriate for melancholic, romantic characters. This phenomenon \u201cexisted in silence\u201d until Herodotus\u2019s discussion of Queen Atossa, according to a Pulitzer-winning book by (*) Siddhartha Mukherjee. Life with this condition is the subject of When Breath Becomes Air by Paul Kalanithi. An experience with this condition led to a 1978 book attacking victim-blaming mentalities which notes how this condition was linked to evil, unlike tuberculosis. For 10 points, Susan Sontag\u2019s Illness as Metaphor is based on her experience with what condition?", "answer": "cancer [accept specific types such as leukemia or breast cancer; accept \u201cCancer\u2019s a funny thing\u201d; prompt on illness or sickness or maladies] &lt;WA, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "23. The first English translation of one of this author\u2019s books came about after Blanche Knopf assumed that that book by this author contained a highbrow sex manual. For their explicit depictions of sexuality, two books by this author became the last to be placed on the Index of Forbidden Books. The thesis of this author\u2019s anti-Freud chapter, \u201cThe Psychoanalytic Point of View,\u201d was borrowed by such authors as Kate Millett. The scope of (*) Camille Paglia\u2019s Sexual Personae was directly inspired by the scope taken by this author, whom Paglia credits as a major influence because she was also \u201craised Catholic,\u201d as illustrated by Memoirs of a Dutiful Daughter. A m\u00e9nage \u00e0 trois with this author\u2019s husband and Olga Kosakiewicz was depicted in She Came to Stay. For 10 points, name this author who wrote about the title group of French intellectuals in The Mandarins, and who also wrote The Second Sex.", "answer": "Simone de Beauvoir &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "24. Much slaughter in the aftermath of this conflict was perpetrated by a red-haired, wild-eyed man with the surname Zombi. Intervention in this conflict was facilitated by the Treaty of Amiens, which lifted a British blockade. Leaders in this conflict announced their political goals at Camp Turel. The U.S. sent naval backing to the victorious side of a portion of this broader conflict called the War of Knives. Controlling this conflict was the responsibility of L\u00e9ger-F\u00e9licit\u00e9 Sonthonax [lay-ZHAY fay-lee-see-TAY son-toh-NOX], an appointee of the (*) Committee of Public Safety. A leader in this conflict later proclaimed himself Emperor Henry I. Yellow fever killed most of the troops sent with Charles Leclerc to suppress the rebels in this conflict, which took place in the colony of Saint-Domingue [san\u00a0doh-MANG]. For 10 points, name this successful slave revolt in which Jean-Jacques Dessalines expelled the French from a Caribbean island.", "answer": "Haitian Revolution [accept any answers referring to a revolt or revolution in Haiti] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}